part 3 chapter 4.
He was much better. He was growing fatter and stronger every day, if it was proper
to speak of days.
The white light and the humming sound were the same as ever, but the cell was a
little more comfortable than the others he had been in.
There was a pillow and a mattress on the
plank bed, and a stool to sit on. They had
given him a bath, and they allowed him to watch himself fairly frequently in a tin basin.
They even gave him warm water to wash with.
They had given him new under clothes and a clean suit of overalls. They had
dressed his varicose also with soothing ointment. They had pulled out of the
remnants of his teeth and given him a new set of dentures.
Weeks or months must have passed. It would have been possible now to keep
count of the passage of time, if he had felt any interest in doing so, since he
was being fed at what appeared to be regular intervals.
He was getting, he judged, three meals in the 24 hours; sometimes he wondered dimly
whether he was getting them by night or by day.
The food was surprisingly good, with meat at every third meal.
Once there was even a packet of cigarettes.
He had no matches, but the never-speaking guard who brought his food would give him a light.
The first time he tried to smoke it made him sick, but he persevered, and spun the
packet out for a long time, smoking half a cigarette after each meal.
They had given him a white slate with a stump of pencil touch to the corner
first he made no use of it. Even when he was awake he was completely topped Often
he would lie from one meal to the next almost without stirring, sometimes asleep,
sometimes waking into vague reveries in which it was too much trouble to open
his eyes. He had long grown used to sleeping with a strong light on his face.
It seemed to make no difference, except that one's dreams were more coherent.
He dreamed a great deal all through this time, and they were always happy dreams.
He was in the Golden Country, or he was sitting among enormous, glorious, sunlit
ruins, with his mother, with Julia, with O'Brien— —not doing anything, merely
sitting in the sun, talking of peaceful things.
Such thoughts as he had when he was awake were mostly about his dreams.
He seems to have lost the power of intellectual effort, now that the
stimulus of pain had been removed. He was not bored, he had no desire for
conversation or distraction.
Merely to be alone, not to be beaten or questioned, to have enough to eat, and to
be clean all over, was completely satisfying.
By degrees he came to spend less time in sleep, but he still felt no impulse to
get off the bed. All he cared for was to lie quiet and feel the strength
gathering in his body.
He would finger himself here and there, trying to make sure that it was not an
illusion that his muscles were growing rounder and his skin taught her
Finally it was established beyond a doubt that he was growing fatter; his
thighs were now definitely thicker than his knees.
After that, reluctantly at first, he began exercising himself regularly.
In a little while he could walk three kilometers measured by pacing the cell,
and his bowed shoulders were growing straighter.
He attempted more elaborate exercises, and was astonished and humiliated to
find what things he could not do.
He could not move out of a war he could not hold his stool out at arm's length,
he could not stand on one leg without falling over.
He squatted down on his heels, and found that with agonizing pains in thigh and
calf he could just lift himself to a standing position.
He lay flat on his belly and tried to lift his weight by his hands.
It was hopeless, he could not raise himself a centimeter But after a few
more days— —a few more meal times even that feat was accomplished. A time came
when he could do it six times running.
He began to grow actually proud of his body, and to cherish an intermittent
belief that his face also was growing back to normal.
Only when he chanced to put his hand on his bald scalp did he remember the
seemed ruined face that had looked back at him out of the mirror.
His mind grew more active. He sat down on the plank bed, his back against the wall
and the slate on his knees, and set it to work deliberately at the task of re-educating himself.
He had capitulated, that was agreed. In reality, as he saw now, he had been ready
to capitulate long before he had taken the decision.
From the moment when he was inside the Ministry of Love—
—and yes, even during those minutes when he and Julia had stood helpless while
the iron voice from the telescreen told them what to do— —he had grasped the frivolity, the
shallowness of his attempt to set himself up against the power of the Party.
He knew now that for seven years the Thought Police had watched him like a
beetle under a magnifying glass.
There was no physical act, no word spoken aloud, that they had not noticed, no train
of thought that they had not been able to infer.
Even the speck of whitish dust on the cover of his diary they had carefully replaced.
They had played soundtracks to him showed him photographs. Some of them were
photographs of Julia and himself.
Yes, even.... He could not fight against the Party any longer.
Besides, the Party was in the right. It must be so: how could the immortal,
collective brain be mistaken?
By what external standard could you check its judgments? Sanity was
statistical. It was merely a question of learning to think as they thought.
Only— The pencil felt thick and awkward in his fingers. He began to write down the
thoughts that came into his head.
He wrote first in large clumsy capitals: FREEDOM IS SLAVERY.
Then almost without a pause he wrote beneath it: TWO AND TWO MAKE FIVE.
But then there came a sort of check. His mind is though shying away from
something, seemed unable to concentrate.
He knew that he knew what came next, but for the moment he could not recall it.
When he did recall it, it was only by consciously reasoning out what it must be:
it did not come of its own accord. He wrote: GOD IS POWER.
He accepted everything. The past was alterable. The pastor never had been
altered. Oceania was at war with East Asia Oceania had always been at war with East Asia
Jones, Aaronson and Rutherford were guilty of the crimes they were charged with.
He had never seen the photograph that disproved their guilt. It had never
existed, he had invented it.
He remembered remembering contrary things, but those were false memories,
products of self-deception.
How easy it all was!
Only surrender, and everything else followed. It was like swimming against
the currents that swept you backwards however hard you struggled, and then
suddenly deciding to turn around and go with the current instead of opposing it.
Nothing had changed except your own attitude: the predestined thing happened in any case.
He hardly knew why he had ever rebelled.
Everything was easy, except———!
Anything could be true. The so-called laws of Nature were nonsense. The law of
gravity was nonsense.
'If I wished Brian had said, 'I could float off this floor like a soap bubble.'
Winston worked it out. 'If he thinks he floats off the floor, and divides
simultaneously think I see him do it, then the thing happens.' Suddenly, like a
lump of submerged wreckage breaking the surface of water, the thought burst into his mind:
'It doesn't really happen. We imagine it.
It is hallucination.'
He pushed the thought under instantly fallacy was obvious.
It presupposed that somewhere or other, outside oneself, there was a 'real' world
where 'real' things happened.
But how could there be such a world? What knowledge have we of anything saved
through our own minds?
All happenings are in the mind. Whatever happens in all minds, truly happens.
He had no difficulty in disposing of the fallacy, and he was in no danger of
succumbing to it.
He realized nevertheless, that it ought never to have occurred to him. The mind
should develop a blind spot whenever a dangerous thought presented itself.
The process should be automatic, instinctive Crime Stop they called it a Newspeak
he's set to work to exercise himself in crime stop He presented himself with propositions—'
—'the Party says the earth is flat', 'the Party says that ice is heavier than
water'— '—and trained himself in not seeing or not understanding the arguments that
contradicted them.
It was not easy.
It needed great powers of reasoning and improvisation.
The arithmetical problems raised, for instance, by such a statement as 2 and 2
make 5 were beyond his intellectual grasp. It needed also a sort of
athleticism of mind, an ability at one moment to make the most delicate use of
logic and at the next to be unconscious of the crudest logical errors.
Stupidity was as necessary as intelligence, and as difficult to attain.
All the while, with one part of his mind, he wondered how soon they would shoot him.
'Everything depends on yourself,' O'Brien had said; but he knew that there was no conscious
act by which he could bring it nearer. It might be 10 minutes hence, or 10 years.
They might keep him for years in solitary confinement, they might send him
to a labor camp they might release him for a while, as they sometimes did.
It was perfectly possible that before he was shot the whole drama of his arrest
and interrogation would be enacted all over again.
The one certain thing was that death never came at an expected moment.
The tradition— —the unspoken tradition: somehow you knew it, though you never
heard it said— —was that they shot you from behind: always in the back of the
head, without warning, as you walked down a corridor from cell to cell.
One day— —but 'one day' was not the right expression; just as probably it was in
the middle of the night: once— —he fell into a strange, blissful reverie.
He was walking down the corridor, waiting for the bullet. He knew that it was
coming in another moment.
Everything was settled, smoothed out, reconciled.
There were no more doubts, no more arguments, no more pain, no more fear. His
body was healthy and strong. He walked easily, with the joy of movement and with
a feeling of walking in sunlight.
He was not any longer in the narrow white corridors in the Ministry of Love,
he was in the enormous sunlit passage, a kilometer wide, down which he had seemed
to walk in the delirium induced by drugs.
He was in the Golden Country, following the foot track across the old rabbit
cropped pasture. He could feel the short springy turf under his feet into the
gentle sunshine on his face.
At the edge of the field were the elm trees, faintly stirring, and somewhere
beyond that was the stream where the day slay in the green pools under the willows.
Suddenly he started up with a shock of horror. The sweat broke out on his backbone.
He had heard himself cry aloud: 'Julia!
Julia!
Julia, my love! Julia!'
For a moment he had had an overwhelming hallucination of her presence.
She had seemed to be not merely with him, but inside him.
It was as though she had got into the texture of his skin.
In that moment he had loved her far more than he had ever done when they were
together and free.
Also he knew that somewhere or other she was still alive and needed his help.
He lay back on the bed and tried to compose himself. What had he done? How
many years had he added to his servitude by that moment of weakness?
In another moment he would hear the of boots outside.
They could not let such an outburst go unpunished. They would know now, if they
had not known before, that he was breaking the agreement he had made with them.
He obeyed the Party, but he still hated the Party.
In the old days he had hidden a heretical mind beneath an appearance of conformity.
Now he had retreated a step further: in the mind he had surrendered, but he had
hoped to keep the inner heart in violet He knew that he was in the wrong, but he
preferred to be in the wrong.
They would understand that— —O'Brien would understand it. It was all confessed in
that single foolish cry.
He would have to start all over again. It might take years. He ran a hand over his
face, trying to familiarize himself with the new shape.
There were deep furrows in the cheeks, the cheekbones felt sharp, the nose flattened.
Besides, since last seeing himself in the glass he had been given a complete new set of teeth.
It was not easy to preserve inscrutability when you did not know what your face looked like.
In any case, mere control of the features was not enough.
For the first time he perceived that if he wanted to keep a secret you must also
hide it from yourself.
You must know all the while that it is there, but until it is needed you must
never let it emerge into your consciousness in any shape that could be given a name.
From now onwards he must not only think right; he must feel right, dream right.
And all the while he must keep his hatred locked up inside him like a ball
of matter which was part of himself and yet unconnected with the rest of him, a
kind of cyst.
One day they would decide to shoot him.
You could not tell when it would happen, but a few seconds beforehand it should
be possible to guess.
It was always from behind, walking down a corridor 10 seconds would be enough. In
that time the world inside him could turn over.
And then suddenly, without a word uttered, without a check in his step, without the
changing of a line in his face— —suddenly the camouflage would be down
and bang! would go the batteries of his hatred.
Hatred would fill him like an enormous roaring flame. And almost in the same
instant bang! would go the bullet, too late, or too early.
They would have blown his brain to pieces before they could reclaim it.
The heretical thought would be unpunished, unrepented, out of their reach forever
They would have blown a hole in their own perfection.
To die hating them, that was freedom.
He shut his eyes. It was more difficult than accepting an intellectual discipline.
It was a question of degrading himself, mutilating himself.
He had got to plunge into the filthiest of filth. What was the most horrible,
sickening thing of all?
He thought of Big Brother. The enormous face (because of constantly seeing it on
posters he always thought of it as being a meter wide), with its heavy black
mustache in the eyes that followed you to and fro, seemed to float into his mind
of its own accord.
What were his true feelings towards Big Brother?
There was a heavy trap of boots in the passage. The steel door swung open with a
clang. O'Brien walked into the cell.
Behind him with a wax and faced officer and the black uniformed guards.
'Get up,' said O'Brien. 'Come here.'
Winston stood opposite him.
O'Brien took Winston's shoulders between his strong hands and looked at him closely.
'You have had thoughts of deceiving me,' he said. 'That was stupid.
Stand up straighter. Look me in the face.'
He paused, and went on in a gentler tone: 'You are improving.
Intellectually there is very little wrong with you. It is only emotionally
that you have failed to make progress.
Tell me, Winston— —and remember, no lies: you know that I am always able to detect a lie—
—tell me, what are your true feelings towards Big Brother?'
'I hate him.'
'You hate him.
Good. Then the time has come for you to take the last step. You must love Big
Brother. It is not enough to obey him: you must love him.'
He released Winston with a little push towards the guards.
'Room 101,' he said